<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Account of the doctrine and discipline of Mr. Richard Davis of Rothwell, in the county of Northampton, and those of his separation with the canons of George Fox, appointed to be read in all the Quakers meetings.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12424</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11912463</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11912463</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50854</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50854)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 47:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Account of the doctrine and discipline of Mr. Richard Davis of Rothwell, in the county of Northampton, and those of his separation with the canons of George Fox, appointed to be read in all the Quakers meetings.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The work of an opponent both of Friends and Richard Davis"--Smith, J. Anti-Quakeriana.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Davis, Richard, 1658-1714.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Covenants (Church polity) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50854:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50854:1"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF THE DOCTRINE AND DISCIPLINE OF Mr. <hi>Richard Davis,</hi> of <hi>Rothwell,</hi> in the County of <hi>Northampton,</hi> And thoſe of his SEPARATION.</p>
            <p>With the <hi>Canons</hi> of <hi>George Fox,</hi> appointed to be Read in all the <hi>Quakers</hi> Meetings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:50854:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50854:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere have been great Contentions, and various Diſputes concerning the Doctrine and Proceedings of Mr. <hi>R. Davis,</hi> of <hi>Rothwell,</hi> and thoſe of his Separation; and as well the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Miniſters, as the People of <hi>England,</hi> are yet in the dark concerning them. Wherefore, having in my hands a Copy of their <hi>Church Covenant,</hi> together with the Explanation thereof, as it was Printed, by their Order, in the Year <hi>1694,</hi> and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to divers whom they ſtile Church-Officers, and others in Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with them; I deemed it not amiſs to communicate the ſaid <hi>Covenant,</hi> with the <hi>Explanation,</hi> to the end the Nation in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral may be acquainted with their Doctrine and manner of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline among themſelves; that, for the future they may not lie under any falſe aſperſions; nor the People of <hi>England</hi> under any miſtakes with regard to them.</p>
            <p>I would not hereby intimate, that every individual Member of this Separation lyeth under the obligation of this Covenant <hi>in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis:</hi> For I'm inform'd, that very few, beſides their Church-Officers, are acquainted with it; and that the new Members are admitted by a ſhorter <hi>Covenant:</hi> But the Myſtery lies here, That the People (as occaſion ſerves) are, by the Officers, informed of the meaning and deſign of their entring into <hi>Covenant</hi> with them, from the Contents of this <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Explanation:</hi> So that, it is the ſame thing (in their ſenſe, and as the Officers ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the matter) as if they had expreſly obliged themſelves to all and every thing contained therein. This is all I think fit to ſay on that Head. Let the <hi>Covenant</hi> plead its own Cauſe, eſpecially coming into the World with the advantage of ſo large a Comment from its own Maſters.</p>
            <p>You have here likewiſe an Account of the ſeveral particulars of their Diſcipline; wherein, I hope, and I verily believe, I have not injured or miſrepreſented them in any reſpect. If I have, and they pleaſe to give publick notice of it, I will be obliged to retract all ſuch particulars, and to give them publick notice thereof in another Edition: For, as I deſign nothing hereby but the ſervice of the Church of God in general, and of this Excellent Eſtabliſh'd Church of <hi>England</hi> in particular; ſo I could not hope that God would permit me to be inſtrumental in either reſpect, ſhould I be found in the number of thoſe who wilfully or negligently Slander or Miſrepreſent their Brethren.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50854:3"/>
            <p>And if the State of that <hi>Separation</hi> be, indeed, ſuch as is ſet down in the following Account (which I take to be the caſe of the greateſt part of the Independent-Congregations throughout the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) I would humbly propoſe it to the Reverend the Clergy, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what Methods are moſt probable to reconcile this Branch of the Separation to the Communion of our Church; and, among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whether the preſent endeavours of forming the Clergy into Societies, purſuant to the Advice of His Grace the Lord Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> may not prove a probable means, through the Bleſſing of Almighty God, to ſecure ſo great an happineſs to this Church and Nation?</p>
            <p>The moſt effectual way to deal with an Enemy ſeems to be to turn his Weapons upon himſelf. If theſe Men ſecure the intereſt of their Societies by a mutual Correſpondence, what hinders but we may do the like? Were they diſperſed as the Miniſters of the Church are; or did they neglect to acquaint each other with thoſe things which relate to their common Intereſt, it would be impoſſible for them to Subſiſt. Indeed the ſeveral Sects among us are ſo many formed Combinations againſt the Eſtabliſh'd Church; and, tho' in many things they differ from each other, as much as Light doth from Darkneſs, yet they ſeem univerſally agreed to Cruſh the Church of <hi>England.</hi> If ſo, the conſequence is plain; <hi>You Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the Church of</hi> England <hi>look about you, and ſuffer not your ſelves to be undone by piece-meal;</hi> which you muſt neceſſarily be without a joint <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion among your ſelves. Nothing is more confirm'd by Reaſon and Experience, than that every pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Work is beſt carry'd on by a friendly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence among the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakers; and certainly the great Work of the Salvation of Souls deſerves our Conſideration in the Methods of the moſt prudential Polity. God Almighty has diſtributed his Talents variouſly among us; and the only way to make them all uſeful, is, firſt, by frequent and familiar Conferences with each other, to diſcover where they lie, and then to employ them as the publick judgment ſhall determine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>After the Copies of theſe Papers were ſent to the Preſs,</hi> Francis Bugg <hi>delivered into my hands a Copy of the</hi> Canons <hi>of</hi> George Fox, <hi>which are judged proper to be Printed with the Account of the</hi> Daviſites; <hi>they being a farther Confirmation of the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Sectaries, in endeavouring to diſtreſs the Church of</hi> England; <hi>and for that reaſon among many others very obvious, I have here preſented you with a juſt view of the ſaid</hi> Canons.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50854:3"/>
            <head>A Church Covenant.</head>
            <q>
               <p>WE the Members of the Church of the Living God, having greatly revolted from our dear Lord, in the deep ſenſe of both former and latter Miſcarriages againſt his Love, Blood, alſo Honour, Crown and Dignity, as King of Souls, Churches and Nations; firmly believing all theſe blotted out, by the Blood of the Lamb, and that we have an undoubted Right to our Father's renewed Manifeſtations of his Pardon and Favour. Do now again give up our ſelves, and all ours, in a moſt ſolemn manner, in this our renewed Act of Covenanting unto the Lord, to be his for ever, ſolemnly promiſing, and engaging in his awful Preſence, and his Angels, in the preſence of Profeſſors, and of the World, to walk continually in him, and with him, and for him; maintaining every manner of way the Faith once deliver'd to the Saints, as to Act and Doctrine, againſt all Oppoſition and Oppoſers whatſoever: And we will in the ſtrength of Chriſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, that all our Holineſs ſhall flow from Faith in Exerciſe working by Love: And thus we ſubject to him as King of Souls.</p>
               <p>We alſo ſolemly Promiſe in the ſtrength of Chriſt, to obſerve all the Forms, Faſhions, Statutes, Laws and Ordinances of his Houſe, eſpecially the great Law of Love to our Lord, and to his Members; reſolving in the Grace that is in Chriſt Jeſus to bear a becoming Evangelical Teſtimony againſt what is contrary to Love, or any other particular Form, Statute, Ordinance, or Law of his whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, either in our ſelves, or any of our Brethren and Siſters of this Church, or any other. We farther Covenant with our dear Lord, and with one another, to diſcharge all relative Duties in this Houſe of God, or in any other Relation we ſtand in whatſoever. And this is our profeſſed Subjection to him as King of <hi>Sion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finally, We promiſe in the ſtrength of Chriſt, and in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of our Royal Husband, to profeſs our Allegiance to him as King of Nations, and to<note n="*" place="margin">The aſſerting of the Kingly Power of Chriſt over Nations, does aſſert alſo the Rights and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Kings, and theſe Magiſtrates that Reign under him.</note> maintain his Rights and Prerogatives, as the King thereof, (to whom the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the World belong) with our Lives, and all dear to us every manner of way, as his Word, Spirit, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, ſhall from time to time call us thereunto.</p>
               <p>And in all thoſe things, we in the Grace that is in our dear Lord, ſhall endeavour to walk according to his Word, and the Explication of this our Covenant, which is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed thereto.</p>
               <p>To the only Wiſe God be Glory and Dominion for ever, and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:50854:4"/>
            <head>AN EXPLANATION OF THE COVENANT.</head>
            <p>WE the Covenanted People, and Church of God, being greatly humbled, that in our former and latter Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we were ſo ignorant and legal; and that it came to paſs, thence, that we have been guilty of ſo many Breaches there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, both we and our Officers; now in the ſteadfaſt believing Views, that all thoſe Breaches are blotted out, and Tranſgreſſions pardoned in him, and for his ſake, who is our conſtant<note n="a" place="margin">1 John 2.1.</note> Advocate, at the Father's Right hand, Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous; and being conſtrained by the Senſe of the boundleſs Love of the Father and the Son, and the paſt and preſent Teſtimonies thereof to our Souls, do profeſſedly and publickly<note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 26.17.</note> this day avouch again ſolemnly the Lord Jeſus to be our<note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 33.22.</note> Judge and King, and Lawgiver, and<note n="d" place="margin">John 8.36. <hi>compar'd with</hi> Rom. 6.8.22.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs our ſelves his Subjects, according to the Tenour of his bleſſed Word, and our former Covenant: And for as much as many of us, if not all of us, were then more or leſs ignorant, how extenſive our former Covenant was, when we engaged to obey<note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 19.8.</note> all his Voice<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 12.25.</note> that ſpeaks from Heaven<note n="g" place="margin">Rev. 19.10.</note> in his Houſe; and becauſe ſince through Grace, we are more enlighten'd by his Spirit from his Word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Generation-work: We think it highly Neceſſary, now to declare our Senſe of thoſe ſeveral particular<note n="h" place="margin">Ezek. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.10.</note> Ordinances, Laws, and Judgments, that we now are engag'd to maintain and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form by the Bowels of his tender Mercies, his holy Word, and our conſent thereto in our former Covenanting: And Firſt, We do judge that our then ſolemn Covenanting as a Church, was a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Declaration and<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 1.9.10</note> Confeſſion with our Mouths, that we had by Faith with our Hearts laid hold of Chriſt Jeſus, as<note n="k" place="margin">Rev. 22.16. 1 Cor. 15.45.</note> our Root<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 7.22.</note> Surety and<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 5.12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Repreſentative. The Grace of Election as being from Eternity fixed on a certain number of<note n="n" place="margin">Ep. 1.4.5.</note> Perſons; and that thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate number of Perſons, for the moſt part ſhould be of a Race, Kindreds, Families and Fatherhoods, not excluding the Seed of Strangers in all Ages, but eſpecially in the latter Age of the World, when the Partition-Wall was to be broken down between <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50854:4"/>
            <p>This is abundantly witneſs'd to by the Word of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.37. <hi>c.</hi> 10.15. which words though they ſpeak literally of literal <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and of the Election of their Seed to ſuceed in their then Church; yet <hi>Iſrael</hi> and their Seed was typical, incluſive and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of the whole Election, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.6. and the Election and Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> out of the World, was to prove and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplifie God's Eternal predeſtinating a certain number for himſelf, to the Adoption of Children. This Truth alſo was atteſted to by the ſeries of Divine Providence in all Ages, chiefly cauſing Electing Grace to run through Godly Families, and filling up the Old and New Teſtament Church with their Seed, yet never excluding the Seed of Strangers. We likewiſe judge, that in our Covenant, we profeſs that by Faith we laid hold of the Eternal Compact, made with our Lord the Redeemer, as our Root, Surety and Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and with us in him and ours too, that were of the true <hi>Iſrael, Iſa.</hi> 59.21. which words though they be ſpoken by God the Father, to our Lord Jeſus, the Surety and Diſpenſator of the New-Covenant, and Teſtament; to his Seed, and Seeds Seed in him; yet he therein is alſo the Meſſenger or Angel of the Eternal Compact. And the New-Covenant it ſelf, in its moſt glorious Adminiſtration<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is but a fuller Copy thereof, promulgated and publiſh'd. We profeſſed then, and now do alſo, to lay hold of this Eternal Compact, as promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated in a more comprehenſive way in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as running with <hi>Noah, Abraham,</hi> the Patriarchs, <hi>David,</hi> the Righteous, the Godly, the Church, and their Seed.</p>
            <p>Rom. 4.16. <hi>compar'd</hi> Gal. 3.8. Gen. 17.17. <hi>compar'd</hi> 2 Cor. 6.18. <hi>with</hi> Acts 2.39. 1 Cor. 7.14. Gen. 12. &amp; 7.13.15.15. <hi>compar'd with</hi> Heb. 14.8. <hi>with</hi> Rom. 11.17. 2 Kings 8.19. 1 Kings 2.4.8.25. Pſal. 132.12. Pſal. 25.13.112.2. 1 Kings 1.2.33. Pſal. 37.25, 26, 89.28, 29.36. 2 Sam. 7.11.19.29. Deut. 1.8.11.9.10.15.4.37. Pſal. 22.30.69.36.102.28. Num. 24.7. Deut. 30.6. <hi>ver.</hi> 19. Pſal, 105.6. Deut. 4.10. Prov. 11, 21. Pſal. 25.13.112.2.127.3, 4, 5.128.3.6. John 5.25. Iſa. 22.24.65.23. Pſal. 72.4.103.17. Prov. 14.25, 26.20.7. Gen. 17.13. Deut. 7.9. Pſal. 122.28. Iſa. 6.13.43.5.44.3, 4, 5.54.3.61.9.65.23 59.21.66.22. Joel. 2.28. Heb. 8.10.11. <hi>compar'd with ult. pars</hi> 11. Rom. 11.16, 17. Acts 2.16, 17. <hi>verſ.</hi> 39. 1 Cor. 17.14. Matth. 10.12, 13. Luke 10.5, 6. Luke 19.9. Acts 16.31. Matth. 19.14. Mark 10.14. Luke 18.16.</p>
            <p>Being therefore convinc'd that in our firſt believing, we laid hold on the Covenant, in the moſt comprehenſive extent of the Grace thereof for us, and ours: And filled with joy and wonder at the Manifeſtations of this Covenant-bleſſings and Privileges declar'd in the Goſpel, as we have in our former Covenanting, ſo in this our Renewal, do now again publickly and ſolemnly give up our ſelves and ours to the Lord Jeſus, our Royal Head and Husband, to be his for ever, now again publickly declaring that he is our Lord,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 45.11.</note> and we will Worſhip him.</p>
            <p>We likewiſe do judge, that in our former Covenant with the Lord, we being<note n="b" place="margin">Pet. 18. Col. 1.13.</note> Choſen and Redeem'd by him,<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 19.27, 28</note> tranſlated into
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50854:5"/> his Kingdom by his Spirit, at Effectual Calling, gave up our ſelves to follow him in the Works of our day, to be Aſſertors of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal Intereſt in the World, and to be witneſſes of this threefold Intereſt of his againſt all Oppoſitions or Oppoſers whatſoever. And now, conſidering we are not our own, but bought<note n="a" place="margin">1 Pet. 18.19.</note> with a price, and redeemed from a vain and fruitleſs Converſation to ſerve him. Mov'd with a ſenſe of his unſpeakable Love to us ward, being greatly humbled, and filled with ſelf-Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that we and our Fathers have too much declined, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook the Cauſe of our Bleſſed King Jeſus, as King of Souls Churches and Nations, do, firmly truſting to the ſufficiency of Grace we have in him, promiſe and reſolve to maintain and abet his Spiritual,<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 3.8. Pſal. 2.6. Rev. 19.16.</note> his Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal Rule over our Souls, his Churches and Nations to the utmoſt: And ſhall be ready, as the Lord ſhall call us to teſtifie againſt the Oppoſers and Uſurpers of this threefold Prerogative belonging to his Crown and Dignity, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying our Lives, Liberties, Eſtates, and all that is dear to us, in our hands to Sacrifice at his Feet for this end and purpoſe. We alſo now are convinced, that in our former Covenanting, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all Duties required, we chiefly engaged our ſelves to that firſt and great<note n="c" place="margin">Joh. 6.29.40. c. 3.16.18.39. <hi>verſes.</hi>
               </note> Command of the Goſpel, <hi>viz.</hi> believing on the Perſon and Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, for<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 11.4.</note> Eternal Life, Acceptance with God,<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 5.1. 1 Pet. 1.8, 9.</note> Peace of Conſcience,<note n="f" place="margin">Joh. 6.53.56, 57.</note> Spiritual Light, Life and Strength, and every thing elſe neceſſary. Therefore being great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="g" place="margin">Jerem. 3.13.</note> aſhamed of the conſtant and notorious breach of the Command of living by Faith, and of our turning aſide from the<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 1.17. Gal. 3.11. Ez. 20. Heb. 3 12. <hi>verſ.</hi> 28.</note> Living God, the Fountain<note n="i" place="margin">Jerem. 2.13.</note> of Living Waters to our own Ciſterns, that will hold no Water, being under deep ſenſe of the Guilt, of our<note n="k" place="margin">John 2.15.</note> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Adultery, and Idolatry, with the World, and the things thereof, our own<note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 3.1. <hi>comp.</hi> Gal. 3.</note> legal Performances, or that call'd Goſpel-Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, our inherent<note n="m" place="margin">Jerem. 2.17. 2 Cor. 12.7. <hi>compar'd with</hi> Cor. 9.19.</note> Qualifications and Spiritual-Enjoyments, which we advanced in the<note n="n" place="margin">Cor. 2.2.</note> room and throne of the Mediator his Blood and Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>We now conſtrained from a ſenſe of his pardoning Grace, and in the ſtrength and virtue of the Blood of the<note n="o" place="margin">Zach. 9.11. Heb. 19.14.</note> Everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ſprinkled on our Conſciences, do reſolve to abide by Faith in Exerciſe in the<note n="p" place="margin">Joh. 15.2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Perſon,<note n="q" place="margin">1 Joh. 4.16.</note> Love and<note n="r" place="margin">Ex. 28.35.43. Pſal. 89.15, 16.</note> Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and as we have<note n="a" place="margin">Col. 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> receiv'd him our Root, Surety and Repreſentative; ſo walking in him by Faith<note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 7.14, 15.</note> that we may continually walk with him<note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 2.1.</note> in the Fellowſhip of the Spirit, conſtantly<note n="d" place="margin">Jam. 1.25.</note> beholding our ſelves by Faith in the glaſs of the perfect Law of Liberty,<note n="e" place="margin">Eph. 4.30.</note> Members of his Glorious Body,<note n="f" place="margin">Col. 2.10.</note> compleat in him and preſented by him in the Body of his Fleſh, through Death,<note n="g" place="margin">Eph. 5.27.</note> not having ſpot or wrinkle, or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, but always<note n="h" place="margin">Col. 1.22.</note> holy, unblamable and unreprovable in his, and his Father's fight; and hereby deriving all Influence and Virtue<note n="i" place="margin">Joh. 1.16.</note>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:50854:5"/> from his Fullneſs for all manner of holy Converſation, and Walk that thus<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> acting continually in his preſence, conſtrain'd by his<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.14.</note> manifeſted Love,<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 4.14, 15.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, 20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 John 18.</note> encouraged by the blotting out of Guilt, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection from our Perſons, Graces and Duty, and they made perfect in him and his Grace; we may always ſeek thoſe things that are Above, where Chriſt is, having our<note n="d" place="margin">Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 2.20.</note> Converſation in Heaven, whence we look for the appearing of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; and being all the day<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 8.6.13.</note> thus ſpiritually minded, watching over our vain wandering Thoughts, we may<note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 62.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> continually make mention of his Name,<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 71.6.</note> Righteouſneſs and<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 63.7.</note> loving Kindneſs, having our Speech always<note n="i" place="margin">Matth. 5.13.</note> ſeaſon'd with Salt, adminiſtring Grace to the Hearers. And being as the Salt of the Earth, and of the Families we dwell in, we may be day by day dying to Sin, and living to Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.<note n="k" place="margin">Tit. 2.12.</note> denying Ungodlineſs, and Worldly Luſts, and living righteouſly, ſoberly, and godly in this preſent World; and with a Converſation<note n="l" place="margin">Phil. 1.27.</note> becoming the Goſpel. We alſo do believe this direct acting of Faith on the Perſon of Chriſt for all things, is<note n="m" place="margin">Jude 3.</note> the Faith of the Goſpel, the Faith once deliver'd to the Saints, which we ought earneſtly to contend for, and to reſiſt all Oppoſitions thereto<note n="n" place="margin">Heb. 12.4.</note> even unto Blood, whether in our Souls, in the Churches, or other Siſter Churches, from the World and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Profeſſors. Hence therefore, laying hold on the ſtrength of Chriſt, (though we know Unbelief will cleave to the leſt of our Performances,) yet we will not plead for it, nor indulge it as a little Sin, much leſs as a Virtue or Grace; but continually watch againſt it, mourn over and loath it, and ſlay it on the Head of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, as the greateſt<note n="o" place="margin">1 John 5.</note> Immorality, becauſe it gives the God of Truth the Lie, and<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> treads the Blood of the Covenant under foot, and more eſpecially the greateſt Unbelief of<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 14.31.</note> queſtioning the Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Fulneſs of Chriſt to ſave us to the utmoſt.</p>
            <p>And though we think it our preſent Duty not to reject all Preaching, whoſe Doctrinal part treads in the ſteps of the firſt Reformers; though the Application be mixed with ſome ſelf-Darkneſs and Legality<note n="a" place="margin">Jude 22.</note> putting difference between them and others, pulling them out of the fire by love and familiarity; yet<note n="b" place="margin">Jude 23.</note> deteſting every Garment of Doctrine, ſo far as it is ſpotted with the Fleſh of Man's Wiſdom: Yet notwithſtanding all thoſe, under what Name or Denomination ſoever, whoſe Tenents corrupt the Doctrine of the Perſon of Chriſt, either denying or leſſening his God-head, his Humane Nature, or myſtical Union of both Natures in one Perſon, or elſe ſeparating the Natures, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding them. As likewiſe all thoſe that add the leaſt mixture to Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, though it be their own acts of Faith in point of Acceptance, Acquittance, and the obtaining of Peace of Conſcience, and who<note n="*" place="margin">T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:50854:6"/>
            <p>and infinitely free in the purpoſe of God in Election, in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and indefinite Manifeſtation of it in the<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 56.10.</note> Perſon of Chriſt, by Redemption, and in<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 4.5. Epheſ. 2.8. 2 Tim. 1.9.</note> actual conferring of it, and manifeſting of it in effectual Vocation to a particular Soul, who alſo make Faith and Repentance foreſeen as Conditions of the Eternal Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and of the Redemption of Chriſt Jeſus, and Faith and Repentance, actual in the Soul, the preparative federal Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of poſſeſſing the Bleſſings of Election in Chriſt our Head; whether it be Chriſt's actual influential Union to us, Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Adoption, or any other Grace whatever: But eſpecially the Perverters of the Goſpel, thoſe moſt refined and ſubtil reſerves of Antichriſt, ſingled out to ſupport its tottering Cauſe in this his laſt War with the Lamb, in theſe laſt days, who<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 1.7.</note> pervert the Goſpel, turning it up-ſide down, aſſerting Faith, Repentance and Holineſs to be given to the Soul before the Perſon of Chriſt, and his Righteouſneſs, denying that bleſſed Order of the tenders and gifts of the Goſpel, which is firſt the<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8.32.</note> Son of God freely, and then all things freely with him; refuſing him and his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to have the<note n="e" place="margin">Col. 1.18.</note> pre-eminence in all things;<note n="f" place="margin">1 Joh. 5.12.</note> even in their actual beſtowment as they ought to have. And beſides all this wickedly intruding a new Law of their own Invention, require<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imperfect Faith and Repentance, and Goſpel Obedience on Man's part, as the imperfect and ſinful Conditions of the Goſpel-Juſtification; thereby<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 3.31.</note> vacating the good old righteous Law of God, ſetting up Terms of obtaining Spiritual Bleſſings, exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing derogatory to the Holineſs of God's Nature, Ways and Laws, and contrary to the freeneſs of his Love and Grace, from the Eternal Purpoſe thereof in Election, even unto the Execution of Electing Grace here and in Glory.</p>
            <p>We do declare and proteſt againſt them and their Doctrine, and likewiſe all thoſe that teach us to<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.31. 2 Tim. 2.1.</note> glory in any thing but the Lord, or be ſtrong in any other Grace, but that Grace that is in Chriſt Jeſus. And do reſolve in the ſtrength of Chriſt's Grace to teſtifie all manners of ways even unto our Blood, againſt any other Goſpel than the Goſpel of our dear Lord, and againſt all other Doctrines than thoſe that are<note n="i" place="margin">Tim. 6.3. Tit. 11.1.</note> according to Godlineſs, and if Men moſt noted for knowledge and Holineſs, or an<note n="k" place="margin">Gal. 1.9.</note> Angel from Heaven preach any other Goſpel, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thoſe Tenents before-mention'd, we do in the preſence and ſtrength of Chriſt promiſe and engage to witneſs againſt them by publick Preaching, and declaring againſt ſuch Principles, by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing from them, and not receiving them to our Houſes, nor bidding them God's ſpeed, according to the Command of the Lord, 2 <hi>John</hi> 10. and by cheerfully and triumphantly deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50854:6"/> our Poſſeſſions, Liberties and Blood, as a Teſtimony againſt them and their pernicious ways, if called thereto.</p>
            <p>We likewiſe now judge, and are perſwaded, that when we Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted with one another to follow the Lord in the Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Goſpel Ordinances, and the performance of all relative Duties in this Church, we profeſſed for all his Eccleſiaſtical Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and<note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 43.11.</note> gave up our ſelves to walk with him and one another, in all the Forms, Laws, Ordinances and Statutes in his Houſe, all which Forms and Statutes are moſt holy, and<note n="a" place="margin">Ez. 43.13.</note> tend to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Holineſs in the<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 15.</note> Holy Citizens of <hi>Zion.</hi> Particularly that we are thereby obliged, and by his Word to love our Lord and King with the<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> higheſt love, and to teſtifie love to him, by keeping all his Commands in his<note n="d" place="margin">Joh. 14.15. Mat. 10.40. c. 18.17, 18.</note> Houſe, to Honour, Reverence, and bow to his Authority and Power lodged therein, and that Authority alſo as cloathing his<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> Officers, Ruling in his Name, to<note n="f" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.3.</note> maintain the Rights and Privileges of any particular Church, his Clergy, his Body,<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.27.</note> againſt all Innovations and Uſurpations from Officers or Members within, from Siſter Churches, or their Officers without, not committing by Delegation the Power and Judgment of the Church to any<note n="h" place="margin">2 Cor. 2.6.</note> minority of it, becauſe thereby the form and faſhion of a Goſpel Church is alter'd, and is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Pattern in the Mount. We farthermore ſee that we ought to maintain towards each other pure Love, and unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all the Roots and Springs, and Effects thereof; and<note n="i" place="margin">1 Rom. 12.9. 1 Pet. 1.22.</note> to watch againſt all defects therein, either in Root or Branch. And therefore we being now griev'd for great decays on us in our love towards the Lord Jeſus, and to one another, do in the preſence and might of our Bleſſed Advocate and Interceſſor, promiſe and reſolve to abide in the Love of Chriſt,<note n="k" place="margin">Joh. 15.9.</note> that our Hearts may be ſtirr'd up to love him, and in love to obey his Royal Laws; particularly to reverence and ſubject to his awful Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in Church Aſſemblies, as if he were himſelf perſonally among us, not affronting his Preſence by a ſlight Carriage, nor his Majeſty there on his Throne, by proud rebellious undervaluing Thoughts, by paſſionate Reflectings, Revilings, or contemptuous Speeches, or by any unbecoming Carriage or Geſture whatever; nor deſpiſing his Dominion in his Houſe, as the<note n="l" place="margin">Jud. 8. 2 Pet. 10.11.</note> filthy Dreamers of old, not grieving nor quenching his Spirit, nor ſtubbornly, nor rebelliouſly deſpiſing and rejecting his Admonitions in his Church, not thinking his Yoak heavy, nor his Burden weighty, but count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it an unvaluable Bleſſing to be under his ſtricteſt and higheſt Watch and Care in his Church.<note place="margin">Matth. 11.30.</note> And if his Children (which God forbid) ſhould, err in the Judgment of any of us, we ſhall by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them, by Reaſoning with them, from Chriſt's Rules, in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50854:7"/> his Bowels, Meekneſs, and with our own, bringing the Advice of other Siſter Churches, moſt faithful to Chriſt, endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them, but ſhall not ſlight them, nor uncover their Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, becauſe they are the Throne of Chriſt's Glory, and the place of the Soles<note n="a" place="margin">Ezek. 43.7.</note> of his Feet, leaſt we ſhould thereby wound his Perſon, his Honour; affront his Majeſty, Crown and Dignity in his Houſe.</p>
            <p>We that are Rulers do in the preſence of Chriſt engage to rule faithfully, diligently<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 12.8.</note> and couragiouſly<note n="c" place="margin">Joſh. 1.6, 7, 9.</note> in Faith, in the fear of God,<note n="d" place="margin">Sam. 23.3.</note> in Meekneſs,<note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 6.1, 2. Tim. 2.25. Lev. 25.43.</note> and Authority,<note n="f" place="margin">Tit. 2.15.</note> hating Covetouſneſs, and Partiality,<note n="g" place="margin">Ex. 18.21.</note> having took the over ſight of the Flock of God which he has purchas'd with his own Blood, and not for filthy Lucres ſake, nor out of conſtraint;<note n="h" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.2, 3.</note> not ceaſing to warn them Night and Day with Tears,<note n="i" place="margin">Acts 20.29. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> watching againſt the Aſſaults of Satan, and their own Corruptions againſt grievous Wolves, that may not ſpare them, and againſt them that may ariſe among themſelves, ſpeaking per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe things, endeavouring to turn them aſide from the Lord that bought them.<note n="k" place="margin">Tim. 1. <hi>to</hi> 8th. Tit. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>to the End.</hi> Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.1.7, 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>We alſo that are ruled in the Church of Chriſt do before our Crowned King, and ſtrengthened with his might, ſolemnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to obey our Rulers ſet over us in the Lord, to follow their Faith, and conſider the ends of their Converſation, to ſubmit our ſelves to them according to the Word of the Lord, for they watch for our Souls as they that muſt give an Account, that they may do it with joy, and not with grief,<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 13.7, 8.17.18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.12.</note> and alſo pray for them.<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.3. 1 Theſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.25. 2 Theſ. 3.1.</note> We do now in the preſence and Grace of our deareſt Lord, that hath redeem'd us, likewiſe engage as a Church of Chriſt in all reſpects to endeavour to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace,<note n="n" place="margin">Eph. 4.3.</note> unfeignedly loving the Perſons of one another, without diſſimulation,<note n="o" place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 12.11. 1 Pet. 22.</note> even when we bear the greateſt Teſtimony againſt their ſin; and as the effects of that endeared brotherly Love to watch<note n="p" place="margin">Theſ. 5.15.</note> over our Brethren and Siſters that they do not decline in their acts of Faith, or turn aſide from the Faith of the Goſpel, conſidering and getting down into one anothers. Hearts continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that we may mutually provoke one another to love, and to good Works; not forſaking the aſſembling our ſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any manner of way, for this good end and purpoſe.<note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 10.24.25</note> Likewiſe with the aſſiſtance of the Spirit of Grace we ſhall endeavour to be very tender of one anothers good Names,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 15.3.</note> Bodies, Health, Lives,<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 5.38.39.</note> and outward Eſtate:<note n="c" place="margin">1 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 1. ad 11 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ev. 19.17</note> We ſhall be ready to aſſiſt one another herein to the utmoſt, being concern'd for the particular welfare of each other therein, as for our own. We no leſs judge it our Duty, not to ſuffer the leaſt Sin, and the leaſt appearance of evil to reſt on one another,<note n="d" place="margin">1 John 1.6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 10.17. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 18.17.</note> as knowing, that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50854:7"/> Sin reſting on a Brother or Siſter, will mar their preſent Communion with the Lord Jeſus.<note n="a" place="margin">1 Joh. 1.6.</note> If the fault be ſecret we ſhall with great Secrecy admoniſh a Brother or Siſter, and out of due regard to their Reputation, forbearing to reveal it to our moſt intimate Boſom Friend<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 18.15.</note> unleſs it be to ſome Officer, if the Caſe be dubious, provided we can but gain by our Loving Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition; But if not, we ſhall in the Strength of the Lord take two or three more<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 18.16.</note> as Witneſſes and Aſſociates with us, farther to warn and beſeech them, in the Bowels and tender Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God in Chriſt, to repent of their evil; yet not preſume to publiſh their Faults to any, but thoſe we take with us; and if any among us publiſh the Miſcarriage of any Brother or Siſter, unleſs it be with a deſign to take the Parties with them as Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, we ſhall faithfully admoniſh them for breaking the Rules of Chriſt in ſo doing. In all the diſcharge of our Duties hitherto, we ſhall carefully watch againſt any Prejudice to their Perſons, by acting and dwelling in the Bowels of Chriſt, and conſidering them as cloath'd with his Righteouſneſs, and clean in God's ſight;<note n="d" place="margin">Cant. 4.6.</note> We alſo leaning on Chriſt's Strength to aſſiſt us, ſhall endeavour to diſcharge our Duty with great Faithfulneſs to them, as well as Tenderneſs, contentedly bearing Oppoſitions from themſelves and others in hard Thoughts, Speeches, Frowns and ſiniſter Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, out of ſincere love to Chriſt's Glory, and the good of their Souls. And if we cannot reclaim them by theſe methods of Mercy and loving Kindneſs, for the Prevention of the farther ſpreading of their evil without delay acquaint the Church with it.<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 18.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> We with him on Thrones of Judgment in his Name and Power, in his Preſence and Might; and in his render Bowels ſhall admoniſh any Brother or Siſter, thus brought before us,<note n="f" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.14.</note> or any whoſe Faults are in their own nature publick,<note n="g" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.20</note> publickly backing our Admonition from his Word and Authority, and his Sovereign Grace committed to us. If we ſee one Admonition begin to take place, we ſhall wait for their thorough Repentance, till we ſee occaſion: And when ever we ſee our Adminiſtration bleſt for their thorough Humiliation, and our Endeavours uſed in a Spirit of<note n="h" place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note> Meekneſs ſucceed; we ſhall be moſt ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them into the Boſom of our Lord and his Church, teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Name, his, and our declar'd Forgiveneſs to them, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving them with all Readineſs and Chearfulneſs, as God for Chriſt's ſake has forgiven us,<note n="i" place="margin">Eph. 4 32.</note> no Man daring to upbraid them in the leaſt, whilſt they walk with us in Love, and the Laws of Chriſt: But if to the diſhonour of the Name of Chriſt, the wounding and hard'ning of their own Souls, and our Grief and Shame, they continue obſtinate and impenitent, we having mourned firſt over
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50854:8"/> them, ſhall in the Name, and Power of Chriſt our King, with enflamed Zeal for his Name, Rule and Houſe, in Tenderneſs, Love and Faithfulneſs to their Souls, cut them off and deliver them to Satan, for the Deſtruction of the Proud Fleſh, that their Spirit may be ſaved in the Day of Chriſt<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 18.17. 1 Cor. 5.2, 3, 4, 5 1 Tim. 1.20. 2 Tim. 3.5. Tit. 3.10. 2 Theſ. 3.14.</note>; and this will we do with the Lord's help in Faith, that this Ordinance ſhall be bleſt for their recovery in God's time<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.5.</note>, if they belong to the Election of Grace. Nevertheleſs, we ſhall continue to love their Perſons, and pray for their recovery, not counting them as Enemies, but warning them as thoſe that yet may approve themſelves to he Brethren,<note n="c" place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.14.</note> when ever we meet them, by charging their Evils on them: And yet will notwithſtanding withdraw all manner of familiarity or Communion with them,<note n="d" place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.5.</note> even that what may be us'd with the moſt profligate Sinners, moſt conſcientiouſly abſtaining from Eating and Drinking with them:<note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.10.11</note> All this we ſhall do in the Exerciſe of the greateſt love to their Perſons, firmly believing theſe are the greateſt Teſtimonies of love that can be ſhown them under ſuch Circumſtances; being aſſur'd that ſuch Carriages towards them conſcientiouſly practiſed in Faith and Love, will be bleſt in time, to ſhame, reclaim and re-inſtate them into Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with the Father and the Son, and his Children; In the conſcientious diſcharge of this Duty towards them, as a Church, and as Members thereof in our reſpective private Stations. We ſhall not be affraid of Anger, Revilings, nor Perſecutions from them, from Churches, Profeſſors, or the World, but willingly and cheerfully ſubmit to all manner of Sufferings<note n="f" place="margin">Luke 17.3.4. 2 Cor. 2.7.8.10.</note> upon this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for Chriſt's ſake; When ever God gives them true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, we ſhall, with great readineſs, cheerfulneſs and tenderheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, forgive them in the Perſon, Name, and Spirit of Chriſt, receiving of them to Communion with the Lord and us, with the greateſt Demonſtrations of Love towards them imaginable,<note n="g" place="margin">Eph. 4.1.32.</note> not only forgiving, but forgetting, and never upbraiding them with their faults<note n="h" place="margin">Col. 3.13.13.</note> (and if any do ſo, calling them to an Account for it) whilſt theſe recover'd Brethren and Siſters walk with us in the Ways and Statutes of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>We alſo being greatly humbled for divers Breaches made among us upon the bonds of Love, do in the Preſence, and reſting on the Grace that is in our Head for us ſolemnly promiſe to our Lord, and one another; watch againſt all thoſe Evils that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, <hi>(viz.)</hi> groundleſs Jealouſies, evil Surmiſings, that are the firſt coolers of brotherly Love: ſo alſo againſt ſecret Whiſperings Tale-bearings and Backbitings, which are the curſed Seed of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and Diſcord ſown in a Church, and in like manner againſt all Wrath, Prejudice and Malice; ſwellings or vauntings over
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50854:8"/> one another, and deſpiſings of one another; Tumults, Seditions, Factions, Clamours, or evil Speaking of, or to one another, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing all manner of Reflections, Reproachings and Revilings for Chriſt's ſake.<note n="a" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.20. Gal. 5.20.21. Eph. 4.31.</note> And no leſs do we engage againſt Wronging one another, as to worldly Goods, Life, or Liberties; againſt all cowardly and covetous refuſings the aſſiſting one another, by Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, Advice and Purſe, to the utmoſt of our Ability,<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 1 Tim. 4.16. Rom. 12.10.13.16.17. Phil. 2.3, 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Gal. 5.13. 2 Cor. Ch. 1.9.</note> and againſt any other thing, or behaviour, that is in the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Royal Law of Love. We think our ſelves in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bound and engag'd to love the Perſons of thoſe that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Dealing, and Excommunication among our ſelves, ſo alſo to love the Perſons of the World, and the Profeſſors that we hope are Godly, tho' they hate us for Chriſt's ſake: But above all, not to abate in our Love in the leaſt towards our Brethren and Siſters, differing from us in ſome Perſwaſions;<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 14.1.</note> though we Judge we are bound by the great Law of Love to endeavour the Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of each other in all things wherein we differ, not by abſurd Cavillings, and fleſhly Objections for Maſtery, but by the Word and Spirit of the Lord in Meekneſs and Tenderneſs, without heats and prejudice, purely for the diſcovery of the Truth,<note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 6.1. 2 Tim. 2.23, 24, 25.</note> that we may be ſtill growing to that ſtature of Fulneſs which is in Chriſt:<note n="e" place="margin">Eph. 4, 13.</note> And ſo came at laſt to ſpeak the ſame things, to be perfectly joyn'd together in the ſame Mind and Judgment,<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10.</note> which will be the Crown and Glory on Churches in the latter Day;<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 52.8.</note> and therefore let us pray in Faith and in the Holy-Ghoſt, uſing all Endeavours for that end and purpoſe, that are according to the Mind of Chriſt, and the Rule of his Word. As to Members of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Churches, we judge we are in Dury bound to love them as our own, (they being alſo of the Body of Chriſt,) and to uſe the ſame Methods towards them in love, when we ſee them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and if we ſee them impenitent, to bring them before the Church, to which they belong. We alſo judge the Vows of the Lord are upon us, to walk in Communion with Siſter Churches, giving them no juſt Offence<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.32.</note> unleſs they take Offence at the matters of our God. We judge 'tis not in our power to Un-church them, tho' they do not come up to ſuch degrees of Purity in Reformation, yet we think our ſelves in Duty bound, and ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engage our Lord to warn them of Errours in Doctrine and Practiſe, eſpecially to teſtifie againſt the Oppoſition to the Faith and Order of the Goſpel; to invite them to go along with us in Generation work, and the Work of Reformation, to warn them in the Bowels of Chriſt, of the careleſsneſs and neglect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, to manage thoſe kind and brotherly Admonitions, by Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Letters, or by Printing, (yet not publiſhing their Faults to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50854:9"/> the World) as ſhall be thought moſt expedient, by the advice of Faithful Siſter Churches; And if this reforms them not, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare Non-Communion with them. And furthermore we the afflicted Children of the Lord in this Church, having in ſeveral days of Prayer, laid low at the Foot of Chriſt, for divers Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects and Remiſſions, in following him in all the Ordinances in his Houſe, do now in his Righteouſneſs, and the Light and Life that is in him, ſolemnly Vow to his Anointed King and Lord, to follow him fully in all his Appointments in his Houſe, and to fill his Houſe as ſoon as we can with ſuch Officers as are mentioned in his Word.<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.28. Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4..11. Acts 20.17.28. Acts 6.1. 1 Tim. 3.12. Rom. 1.16. 1 Cor. with 1 Tim. 5.6. <hi>v.</hi> 17.</note> We alſo engage conſcientiouſly and conſtantly to<note n="b" place="margin">Acts 1.14.21. Acts 2.42. Heb. 6.2. Mat. 3.56.</note> attend on the publick Miniſtry of the Church, to joyn with them in the Ordinances of Chriſt, ſuch as Baptiſm,<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.23, &amp;c.</note> and the Lord's Supper;<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.23.24. to <hi>v.</hi> 34.</note> Preaching, Prophecying,<note n="e" place="margin">Acts 1.14. Acts 2.4.2.</note> Praying,<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 26.30. 1 Cor, 14.16. Col. 3.16. Rev. 5.9. Rev. 14.31.</note> Praiſing by Vocal Singing, Teaching and Admoniſhing one another in our Meetings, by Doctrine, Exhortation, or Revelation, alſo in Pſalms, Hymns, and Spiritual Songs, according to the Command of our Lord Jeſus.<note n="g" place="margin">Zech. 14.17. Acts 2.42.</note> We alſo ſolemnly engage to come up to ſolemn Days appointed by the Church, and likewiſe to come up unanimouſly to Church-Meetings,<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 10.9.10.</note> to govern with our Lord in his Houſe, and keep it clean, to admit Members upon a Confeſſion with their Mouths, that they have believ'd on Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs with their Hearts,<note n="i" place="margin">Ez. 43.10.11.</note> with alſo a Profeſſion of their Allegiance to follow <hi>Sion</hi>'s King in the Laws and Statutes of his Houſe,<note n="k" place="margin">2 Cor. 8.5.</note> and for that end their ſolemn Covenanting with the Lord, and us. Likewiſe to admoniſh Offenders, and to caſt out, if need be, and to give our joynt Advice and Aſſiſtance in all caſes of Difficulty Therefore we do again come under our ſolemn Vows to the Lord,. to frequent all the Aſſemblies of <hi>Sion,</hi> unleſs hindred by length of Days, weakneſs of Body, or ſuch extraordinary Occaſions, that may be ſufficient Reaſons in the ballance of the Sanctuary for our abſence at any time. We as a Church, and each Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in our private Capacities, do in Chriſt's Preſence and Strength engage to watch over our Brethren and Siſters, that they be not negligent and remiſs in attending the Aſſemblies and Services of the Church. We alſo ſolemnly Promiſe to the Lord and to one another, that we will not keep away from the Lord's Table, upon the account of Satan's Temptations, or our own Unbelief, or upon the account of Offence given to us by any Brother and Siſter; Brethren and Siſters, and that we will not in Chriſt's Strength diſobey him our King, deſpiſe his Ordinances, ſin againſt our holy Fellowſhip, and puniſh our ſelves for the Offence of others.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:50854:9"/>
            <p>We likewiſe engage to the Lord and one another, to keep the Church viſible, as a City ſet on a Hill, in all its Laws, Statutes and Adminiſtrations, and to appear publick there in the face of all Oppoſition whatſoever.</p>
            <p>We do alſo reſolve as a Royal Prieſthood in our Profeſſion Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, Walk and Converſation, with the loſs of our Names, Lives and Liberties, our Reputations and Eſtates, and every thing that is dear unto us; to bear our Teſtimony againſt all falſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Worſhip whatſoever. To wit, againſt the Mother of Harlots and all her Daughters; and we likewiſe proteſt againſt Idolatry, Superſtition, Impoſition and Perſecution, where ever and whatſoever. And in love to him, and Honour of his Crown, who firſt loved us, we reſolve and engage by the aſſiſtance of the Grace that is in him, to have nothing to do to go near their falſe Worſhip, unleſs it be to teſtifie againſt 'em, that we will withdraw from 'em, and that we will not joyn with thoſe that joyn with 'em, who are confederates againſt Chriſt. And this Teſtimony we engage in Chriſt's Preſence to bear every way, and in every place whatever, even in Courts of Judicature, and at the Place of Execution if call'd thereto. Furthermore, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing convinced and humbled, that we and our Fathers have either ſelfiſhly neglected or cowardly betray'd the Intereſt of our Bleſſed Lord, as King of Nations; and do humbly waiting for his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his ſtrength, reſolve that we ſhall from time to time, as he enlightens us, leads us and calls us, be ready to part with our All, in aſſerting and maintaining all his Royal Prerogatives and Rights, as King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, againſt all Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Oppoſition whatever to his Crown and Dignity, to whom the Kingdoms of the Earth belong, and that we ſhall faithfully teſtify againſt any that ſhall thus betray his Cauſe and Intereſt. And alſo when we in our late Covenant engaged to perform all relative Duties, not only in the Houſe of God, but alſo elſewhere; we judge that by the Word of the Lord, and our own Vows, we are obliged to fill each his place, and diſcharge our relative Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in our reſpective Stations and Capacities. We therefore great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grieved for divers Neglects and Breaches therein, do engage in the Preſence, Power and Spirit of the Lord Jeſus, to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual recourſe to the Blood of Sprinkling, to waſh away the Stains thereof, and do in his Preſence and Strength promiſe to watch againſt all ſuch Breaches of his Rules in our ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>We do alſo Covenant with the Lord, and with one another, to ſeek the good and welfare of the Nation we live in, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.10. to be ſubject to thoſe higher Powers the Lord Jeſus ſets over us,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50854:10"/> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12. Nor only for Wrath, but for Conſcience ſake, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tribute to 'em as God's Miniſters, <hi>v.</hi> 6. yet as free Servants of God; but not uſing our Liberty for a Cloak of Maliciouſneſs, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16. and hereby putting to ſilence the Ignorance of fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Men, <hi>v.</hi> 15. We that are Husbands do promiſe to love our Wives, as Chriſt does the Church, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25. And as our own Bodies, <hi>v.</hi> 28. leaving all and cleaving to our Wives, <hi>v.</hi> 38. not being bitter againſt 'em, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.19. dwelling with 'em according to Knowledge; giving Honour to 'em as the weaker Veſſels; forbearing to ſin afore 'em, and covering their Infirmities, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heirs together of the Grace of Life, that our Prayers may not be hindred. We alſo that are Wives Covenant with the Lord and with one another, to love and ſubmit our ſelves to our own Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands as unto the Lord, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.22. being ſubject to 'em, as the Church is unto Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 24. having our Converſation chaſte with Fear and Reverence to our Husbands, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.2. Avoiding the Pride of Apparel, and conformable Faſhions, <hi>v.</hi> 3. being meek and quiet in our Spirits and Deportments in our Houſes, <hi>v.</hi> 5. our Obedience being founded on love without fear and ſlavery, <hi>v.</hi> 6. being Sober, lovers of our Husbands and Children; Diſcreet, Chaſte, keepers at Home, obedient to our Husbands, 1 <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.4, 5. We that are Parents engage to the Lord and to his Church to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge all Duties to our Children, as the Lord enlightens us and ſtrengthens us, teaching 'em in the way wherein they ſhould go, bringing 'em up in the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord, not provoking 'em to wrath by unjuſt and cruel Carriage, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.4. We that are Children promiſe to the Lord and his Church in the ſtrength of his Grace to Obey our Parents in all things in the Lord, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.20. We that are Maſters and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes alſo Covenant with the Lord and his Church, in the ſtrength of Chriſt, to carry it juſtly and mercifully towards our Servants, forbearing Threatnings, and unchriſtian Violence, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.9. We that are Servants Covenant with the Lord and his People, to Obey them that are our Maſters according to the Fleſh, with Fear and Reverence; not with Eye-ſervice as Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leaſers, but in ſingleneſs of Heart as unto Chriſt, as having a reſpect to his Eye on us more than Man's, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.5, 6. <hi>c.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.22. endeavouring to pleaſe 'em in all things, not contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or anſwering again, nor robbing 'em of their Time nor Goods, but ſhewing all good Fidelity, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.9, 10. and thus we will carry it, not only to godly and gentle Maſters or Miſtreſſes, but alſo to thoſe that are Carnal and Froward, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. Laſtly, we promiſe to the Lord and his Church, to carry it with Juſtice and Mercy, to the Names, Eſtates, Bodies and Souls of our Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50854:10"/> Neighbours, forbearing to Reproach 'em, and wound their Reputation, to do 'em the leaſt Damage in their Eſtates, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to their Bodies, or laying ſtumbling blocks in the way of their Souls: And thus as much as in us lies we follow Peace with all Men, but with Holineſs, which conſiſts in avoiding Joyning with 'em in the leaſt Evil, or give up to 'em the leaſt Truth of Chriſt, or for to pleaſe 'em in denying the leaſt thing that relates to the Faith and Order of the Everlaſting Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Now to ſum up all, we finally Promiſe and Covenant with the Lord and his Church, in the Preſence and Grace of Chriſt, to obey his whole Will revealed in his Word, explained to us by his Spirit, nor do we by this Covenant limit our ſelves to what is herein contain'd, but engage to wait on the Lord for further diſcoveries of his Mind and Will, believing he will reveal it to us, and if there be any Wood, Hay, or Stubble, in this Form of Covenant, we are content it ſhould be burnt up by the Holy Spirit. We alſo ſolemnly promiſe and engage in the Preſence and Strength of Chriſt, whatever farther diſcoveries of Light may be firſt manifeſted to the meaneſt of us, we will examine it by the Word of God, and in fervent Prayer, and ſhall be far from rejecting or fighting againſt it, unleſs it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to us by the Spirit, after due ſearch, that it is of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</p>
            <p>We do now ſolemnly declare, that we do not hereby, not will not impoſe on the Conſciences of our Brethren and Siſters, that are amongſt us, in Indifferences of leſſer moment, that walk conſcientiouſly up to their Light, exhorting all to be faithful thereto, and of a peaceable Spirit, ready to follow on to know the Lord.</p>
            <p>We engage likewiſe, and ſolemnly promiſe all of us, that if any of us ſhould heſitate about any Doctrine or Practiſe,<note place="margin">☜</note> contrary to the Faith and Practiſe of the Church; to conſult with the Church and its Officers, at leaſt for our own Satisfaction, if not for the Churches Conviction, (provided it be right) or before any of us do cordially and thoroughly eſpouſe it.</p>
            <p>The whole Will of God revealed in his Word, we ſolemniy promiſe and engage in the Love, Strength and Preſence of the Lord, and his holy Angels and Believers, to conſent to and approve of, to comply with, to ſtudy to be found in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of, and make the Rules of our holy Walk to be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for the leaſt breach thereof, and to have continual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Blood of Sprinkling, as cleanſing from the ſtains thereof to abide in the Perſon and Righteouſneſs of Chriſt by Faith, who in our room and ſtead, as one ſurety has perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50854:11"/> performed theſe our Engagements and Preſents, our Obedience, as wrapt up in his Righteouſneſs, through the hands of our High-Prieſt, in the Exerciſe of our Royal Prieſthood to our God and Father, for the Honour of his Name, the commendation of his Holy Religion, as the Teſtimonies of our Love, Thankfulneſs, and Gratitude towards him.</p>
            <p>Now to him that hath waſhed us from our Sins in his own Blood, and has made us Kings and Prieſts, to God and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to him be Glory and Dominion for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>There are ſome Errata's in this <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Explanation</hi> which the Publiſher did not think fit to alter, they being the ſame in the Copy.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>THE DISCIPLINE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ANno</hi> 1692, <hi>Richard Davis,</hi> who ſtiles himſelf Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Rothwell,</hi> in the County of <hi>Northampton,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Members according to the Subſtance of the Form under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written, which he called, <hi>A Church Covenant,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paſtor.</hi> Do you in the preſence of God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, and this Congregation here preſent, <hi>Give your ſelves up unto us,</hi> as we have given our ſelves to one another,<note n="(a)" place="margin">To juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this they urge 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5.</note> 
               <hi>to walk with us and only us,</hi> in all Goſpel Ordinances, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of all Relative Duties, as God ſhall help you?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paſtor.</hi> So do we, in the aforeſaid awful Preſence, Covenant to walk with you in the ſame, and, if we ſhall be let into any further Light, to make it known to you.</p>
            <p>In the time of <hi>Thomas Browning,</hi> the Predeceſſor of <hi>Richard Davis,</hi> the cuſtom, at <hi>Rothwell,</hi> had been to have their Paſtor Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the Elders of other Churches; but when <hi>Davis</hi> was made choice of for their Paſtor, the Church at <hi>Rothwell</hi> pleaded that they were Independent, and conſequently ought to have the privilege of Ordaining their own Paſtor, and accordingly Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>R. Davis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This occaſioned ſome Differences in the Congregation, and, by degrees, others aroſe; whereupon, about the Year 1694, the other Covenant was Framed and Printed, with the Explanation by way of Renewal of their former Covenant, to which the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50854:11"/> part aſſented and remained Members: Thoſe who did not, when they had pleaded for a diſmiſſion and were refus'd it, join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with other Congregations according to their diſcretion, and were cut off by thoſe at <hi>Rothwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their Church Officers<note place="margin">Church Officers.</note> are of three ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Paſtor. 2. El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. 3. Deacons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Paſtor<note place="margin">Paſtors.</note> is choſen by the conſent of the major part of the Congregation, and is Ordained by Impoſition of the Hands of the Elders of the Congregation. His Office is to Preſide, to Teach, to Conſecrate the Elements in the Sacrament, and to Baptize.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Elders,<note place="margin">Elders.</note> who are choſe likewiſe by the Congregation, and ſet apart by Impoſition of Hands, and are of two ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Preaching Elders, whoſe Office is to Preach and Rule. 2. Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elders, whoſe Office is to Rule only: Not but that they may Preach occaſionally, if they pleaſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Deacons,<note place="margin">Deacons.</note> who alſo are choſen by the Congregation, and ſet apart to that Office by Impoſition of Hands. Their Office is to take care of the Three Tables, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The Lord's Table. 2. The Paſtors Maintenance. 3. The Poor. They Collect the Alms of the Congregation every Sacrament-Day, which is ordinarily once every three Weeks or Month. They carry the Bread and Wine to the Communicants. They have the Cuſtody of the Money in Bank, and are accountable for it: This is a ſmall Sum reſerv'd to anſwer any particular extraordinary occaſion. Out of theſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers the Elders are generally choſen, not always.</p>
            <p>They hold, that the Power of each particular Officer is equal with the reſt, only the Paſtor preſides for Order ſake; and if the Paſtor and Officers cannot agree, the Majority of the Congregation in a Church Meeting determines the matter.</p>
            <p>The Ordination of the Paſtor is by Impoſition of the Hands of the Elders: The Ordination of Elders and Deacons by Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Hands of the Paſtor and Elders. Herein they tie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to no form of Words; they ſtand during the Ceremony, and Pray before and after, either the Paſtor or Elders, or both.</p>
            <p>This is always done at their Church Meetings, where none have any Buſineſs beſides the Members, and where none elſe uſually are preſent.</p>
            <p>The Paſtor is maintain'd by thoſe in Covenant with him.<note place="margin">Maintenance of the Officers.</note> There is a Book for Subſcriptions; and if any Member, able to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, refuſe, he is requir'd to give his Reaſons in publick; and if they are not approv'd of, and he continue to refuſe, he is dealt withal as a Sinner. This Subſcription Money is by the Deacons collected quarterly and paid to the Paſtor.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50854:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> That this Subſcription Money is not the whole of the Paſtors Maintenance; becauſe the Women, whoſe Husbands are of other Congregations, do privately contribute, and that libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally; and 'tis obſerved, That the ſeparate Congregations have generally more Women than Men. Thoſe likewiſe of meaner condition among them, who have dependance on any of the Church of <hi>England</hi> for a Livelihood, are oftentimes excuſed from Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing, tho' not from contributing in proportion to their Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</p>
            <p>The Members only are obliged to Subſcribe; but the whole Aſſembly is exhorted to contribute when the Deacons on the Sacrament-Days collect the Alms of the Congregation. Theſe Collections are made every Sacrament-Day; and out of theſe the ſeveral Officers, if they want, are ſupplied.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Meetings.</note>Their Meetings are of four kinds, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. On every Lord's Day, for Prayer and Preaching, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Sacrament, as often as it is Adminſtred; likewiſe for receiving the publick acknowledgments of thoſe, whoſe <note place="margin">☞</note>Crimes have been publick. The acknowledgments here made, are generally by ſuch perſons as have complied too far with the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Solemn Days appointed by the Congregation; the uſual occaſions whereof, are to ſeek the Mind of God, in relation to any differences in their Church; on the Death or Reſignation of the Paſtor; when any Officer or other uſeful Perſon hath forſaken them; when there are any Calamities befallen them, or any Mercies beſtowed on their Church, or the Nation: They ſay the Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days obſerved by the Church of <hi>England</hi> are all Popiſh. <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſs, Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſuntide</hi> they regard not. State Faſts and Thankſgivings they do allow of.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Church Meetings, which conſiſt only of the Members, <hi>i.e.</hi> thoſe who are in Covenant. Theſe are for regulating Matters in their Church; and are held ſome Day in the Week before they Break Bread. They begin with Prayer, adviſe together, admit Members, admoniſh Offenders, excommunicate the Obſtinate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Penitent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ordinary Pennance requir'd, is an acknowledgment of the Crime at theſe Meetings, with promiſe of future amendment.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Meſſengers Monthly Meetings, which conſiſt of the Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates or Meſſengers from all the Siſter Churches, <hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed after their Model, within a certain Precinct; for which every Church appoints two or more according to its diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Theſe are commonly the Paſtor and one or two Elders of each Congregation. The manner of appointing them as follows, <hi>viz.</hi> The Paſtor gives publick notice in a Church Meeting, That
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50854:12"/> on ſuch a Day the Meſſengers Meeting is to be, and deſires them to ſend their Meſſengers, and ordinarily propoſes himſelf and one more, and, if they conſent, deſires them to lift up their Hands (the uſual ſign whereby they ſignifie their conſent or approbation.) At theſe Meetings they Communicate to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the concerns of their particular Churches; give account of all Members cut off, and of all other proceedings that are material. If any difficulties have ariſen in the particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, the reſpective Meſſengers report to their own Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations what was the opinion or determination of the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives of the ſeveral Churches.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe Meetings above-mentioned,<note place="margin">☜</note> at <hi>Rothwell</hi> they have private Cabals of truſty Men to prepare matters to be propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at their Church-Meetings, thereby to prevent any nice can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſing matters of Controverſie before the Members, for fear of raiſing or ſomenting Diſputes among them.</p>
            <p>Their method in the admiſſion of Members,<note place="margin">Admiſſion of Members.</note> is, <hi>viz.</hi> At their Church-Meetings the Paſtor gives notice to the Aſſembly, that there are certain perſons who deſign to offer themſelves to the Church, and asks their conſent that they may be called in and Examined; which obtained, every Perſon is called in by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and Examined; touching his Converſion, Faith, Experiences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then ordered to withdraw: The Examination finiſhed, the Paſtor enquires of the Members whether they are willing to receive ſuch and ſuch particular Perſons, and, if the Majority ſignifie their conſent by lifting up their Hands, they are called in, and by the Paſtor acquainted that the Church is ſatisfied of their Experiences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and will admit them by and by. When every particular Perſon hath been thus dealt withal; the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor receives them according to the ſubſtance of the ſhorter Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and in a Book which they keep (different from that which contains the Subſcriptions for the Paſtors maintenance) <hi>each Perſon writes his own Name.</hi> This Practice they ſay is warranted, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the 44th Chap. the 5th Verſ.</p>
            <p>After the ſtricteſt enquiry it appears that the Printed Covenant with the Explanation, hath been delivered to very few, and thoſe Select Perſons; ſo that it ſeems to have been chiefly deſigned for the Elders, with whom the Members are to conſult. It doth not appear that it hath been refuſed to any Member who hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to buy it; tho' the generality have either not heard of it, or not ſeen it. Thoſe who have it are obliged not to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate it to any Stranger, or the World (as they term all others) who are not of their way.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:50854:13"/>
            <p>When the Congregation is aſſembled, the Preacher (whether Paſtor or Elder) begins with Prayer,<note place="margin">Behaviour in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> the People generally ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (they look upon thoſe as lazy who ſit and will not ſuffer any Man to be covered): When Prayer is ended, they cover their Heads, and ſit or ſtand, as they pleaſe, during the Sermon. This is the whole of their Behaviour and Service, unleſs they Sing an Hymn, which they ordinarily do.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Baptiſm.</note>They Baptize both Children and Adult, in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, without the Sign of the Croſs, Praying before and after. None Pray on this occaſion but the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, and none but he may Baptize, and that only the Members, or Children of the Members of his own Congregation. No Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are admitted. The Parents are charged in behalf of their Children; the Adult takes the charge upon himſelf. If one of the Parents be a Member, it's ſufficient to entitle the Child to their Baptiſm. Where the Parents are of different Perſwaſions they Baptize the Children privately. They ordinarily Baptize at a Church Meeting, and in any private Houſe if deſired. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, tho' Baptized by them, are not eſteemed Members, unleſs, when they arrive at Years of Diſcretion, they enter into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as the other Members have done.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Breaking of Bread.</note>Every Member is required to receive the Sacrament as often as it is adminiſtred. The Table ſtands in the midſt of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, near the Pulpit. The Paſtor ſits in his Chair near the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the Receivers on Forms round about it; the People, as Spectators, at ſome ſmall diſtance behind them.</p>
            <p>The Paſtor Prays (all ſtanding) and craves a Bleſſing on the Bread; then ſets it apart in almoſt the ſame Words which the Church of <hi>England</hi> uſes; then breaks it into ſmall pieces and puts them on divers Plates, ſaying, whilſt he is breaking, <hi>Thus was our Lord's Body torn, mangled, broken,</hi> &amp;c. The Bread thus broken is carried in the Plates, by the Deacons, to the ſeveral Receivers. The Paſtor ſits in his Chair Eating with the reſt.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Bread is Eaten, the Paſtor Prays; then pours out the Wine, ſaying, <hi>Behold the Blood of Chriſt poured out for thee, and for me, and for all of us,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Drink ye all of this, drink large draughts of the Love of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. as he thinks moſt proper to expreſs himſelf. Then he drinks and gives to the Deacons. When all have drank, the Paſtor Prays, an Hymn is Sung, and the Aſſembly is diſmiſſed.</p>
            <p>They forbid all private Prayer at this Ordinance, ſaying, The Paſtors Prayers are ſufficient. They eſteem 'it a Memorial only: Examine none before they come, ſaying, There is no need of any more Preparation at that time than any other. In the abſence or ſickneſs of the Paſtor there muſt be no Sacrament.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50854:13"/>
            <p>If any Member plead Conſcience for leaving them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a diſcharge, and offer his Reaſons in publick;<note place="margin">Diſmiſſion of Members.</note> they will not give him a diſcharge, unleſs it be with a Teſtimonial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending him to ſome Congregation they approve of. If he refuſe to joyn with ſuch a Congregation as they approve of, and withdraw himſelf from them, they cut him off as an Apoſtate. No pretence of Conſcience will prevail with them to allow any to joyn with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or the Presbyterians, or Quakers, or the ſtrict Baptiſts. They plead they cannot diſcharge them, becauſe thoſe Churches they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to joyn with, do not walk accordingly to the Rule of God's Word; ſaying, ſhould we ſuffer you, we ſhould comply with you in Sin. Therefore the Officers charge them with their Covenant, and Command them to obey the Authority of Chriſt inveſted in them, upon pain of the diſpleaſure of the King of Heaven.</p>
            <p>When any Member revolts,<note place="margin">Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> the method they profeſs to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, is, To ſend for him to give his Reaſons to the Church; if he comes they admoniſh him to return; if he does not come, they empower one or two Meſſengers to go to him, and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him in the Name of the Church; this they do a ſecond time: If this prevails not (after ſome time allowed according to their diſcretion) they ſend Meſſengers to acquaint him that on ſuch a Day they intend to cut him off; and when they have cut him off, they ſend to acquaint him with it. This is always done at a Church Meeting.</p>
            <p>If the Paſtor be Living, it is his Sole Privilege to pronounce the Sentence of Excommunication. The Method is, to Pray, and Exhort the People on this occaſion, and then to pronounce the Sentence in theſe or the like Words, <hi>viz. I do, in the Preſence of God, with the judgment and conſent of this Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">To juſtifie this they urge 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>deliver</hi> A. B. <hi>unto Satan, for the deſtruction of the Fleſh, to be buffeted by him, that his Soul may be ſaved in the Day of the Lord.</hi> They then blot his Name out of the Book of Subſcriptions (which they call the Book of Life) and henceforth avoid him, according at it is ſet down in the <hi>Explanation of the Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any ſick<note place="margin">Sick.</note> Perſon deſires it, the Paſtor and ſome Elders repair to him and Anoint him, Praying over him. They dip their Fingers in a Porringer or Sawcer of Oyl, wherewith they rub the Temples of the Sick Perſon.</p>
            <p>They traduce the Publick Prayers of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as Idolatrous and Antichriſtian, the Miniſters as ſcandalous in their Lives, negligent in their Duty, forſaking their own Articles, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal in their Adminiſtrations, legal in their Preaching, without the Power of Godlineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50854:14"/>
            <p>They call all Churches and Worſhip falſe which are not Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd by a Covenant like theirs, <hi>i. e.</hi> all Churches that are not Independent.</p>
            <p>They engage not to go near theſe Churches; and if any of the Members occaſionally go, and are uncovered there, they interpret ſuch uncovering an aſſent to the Prayers, and deal with ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as Sinners, cutting them off, if they do not teſtifie their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>They ſay, That God hath before ordained whatſoever comes to paſs, even the worſt of Sins, and that Sinners cannot avoid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them; That it is to no purpoſe to pray for, or endeavour after Repentance; becauſe the Sins of the Elect, paſt, preſent, and to come, are already forgiven; and therefore they ought to pray only for the Manifeſtation of their Pardon.</p>
            <p>They look upon themſelves obliged to Trade with their own Members, or thoſe of their Way, if poſſible: When ſome have done otherwiſe, the Paſtor hath publickly declared, in their Church Meetings, that it was their Sin, and the Elders have join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him. 'Tis a general Rule among them; <hi>Trade with any rather than the Church of</hi> England. In order to perpetuate this Schiſm, <hi>Davis</hi> breeds up Young Men in his Houſe.</p>
            <p>According to the beſt account I can get, There are about Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen gathered Congregations of this Separation under ſetled Paſtors; the Members whereof are computed to be between two and three Thouſand.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe, they have divers Congregations for Prayer and Preaching, which have no ſetled Paſtors, nor any Adminiſtration of the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>When any of the Hearers deſires to be admitted a Member of any particular Congregation, notice is given to that Congregation, who, at their Church Meeting, appoint the Paſtor, with ſome El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Deacons, to go and hold a Church Meeting near the place where ſuch Hearer dwelleth, and to examine and admit him, as before ſpecify'd.</p>
            <p>When they have gained a competent Number of Members in any part, they fix a Paſtor among them, and embody them.</p>
            <p>This was the ſtate of the Separation, at <hi>Rothwell,</hi> about the Year 1696, which, as I underſtand, has receiv'd no conſiderable alteration ſince that time.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50854:14"/>
            <head>THE CANONS OF <hi>GEORGE FOX.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>Friends Fellowſhipp muſt be in the Spirit and all Friends muſt know one another in the Spirit and Power of God</head>
            <p>Firſt IN all the Meetings of the County two or three being ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from them to goe to the Generall Meetings for to give notice one to another if there be any that walkes not in the truth, and have beene convinced and gone from truth and ſoe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonoureth God, that ſome may be ordered from the meeting to goe to exhort ſuch, and bring into the next Generall meeting what they ſay.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly If any that profeſſe the truth that follows pleaſures drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe gameings or is not faithfull in their callings and dealings, nor honeſt nor juſt but runs into debt and ſoe brings a Scandall vppon the truth; Friends may give notice to the Generall meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (if there be any ſuch) and ſome may be ordered to goe and exhort them and bring in their anſwer the next Generall meeting</p>
            <p n="3">3ly And if any goes diſorderly together in Marriage contrary to the Practice of the holy men of God and aſſemblies of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in all ages, who declared it in the aſſemblies of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous when they took one another (all things being cleere, and they both being free from any other, And when they doe goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and take one another let there not be leſſe then a dozen Friends and Relations preſent (according to your former order)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50854:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> having firſt acquainted the mens meeting, and they have cleerneſſe and vnity with them, And that it may be Recorded in a Book ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word and Commandement of the Lord, and ſuch if any walk contrary to the truth herein let ſome be ordered to ſpeak to them and give notice thereof to the next Generall meeting</p>
            <p n="4">4ly And all that be widdows (which have Children) and doe intend to Marry let Query be made what ſhee hath done for her Children: If there be noe will made then let ſuch part of her late husbands Eſtate be ſet out for her Children as is equall and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to truth, and what they can doe afterwards let them do alſo, And where there is a will made let thoſe Legacies and Portions be improved and ſecured before Marriage for the Children of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed with what more they can doe for them and then when theſe things are done let them be recorded in a Book at the next Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Meeting</p>
            <p n="5">5ly And alſo all Widdowes in all your ſeveral meetings, let them be taken notice of and Informed and incouraged in their outward buſineſſe, that there be not any hinderance to them in their inward growth, and ſo carefully lookt after that they may be nouriſhed and cheriſhed, and ſoe preſerved in the truth that love may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed And if they have many Children to put out Apprentices or Servants, that may be a burthen to them to bring vp: then let Friends take care to eaſe them by putting them forth as may be meete. Let all theſe things be looked into by every meeting And notice thereof given to the next Generall meeting: And then ſome ordered to ſee that all things are done according to truth and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe</p>
            <p n="6">6ly And all ſuch as Marry by the Prieſt of <hi>Baal</hi> who are in the Rough hands of <hi>Eſau</hi> and fiſts of wickedneſſe, and bloody hands, and who have had their hands in the blood of our Brethren, and who are the cauſe of all this Baniſhment of our Brethren And hath ſpoiled ſo many of their goods caſting into priſons and keepes many hundreds at this day, And ſuch as goes to them for wives or husbands muſt come to judgment and condemnation of that Spirit that led them to <hi>Baal</hi> and of <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts alſo, or elſe Friends that keeps their habitations muſt write againſt them and <hi>Baal</hi> both, For from <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the <hi>Revelations</hi> you never read any of the Prieſts that married people But it is Gods ordinance and whom God joynes together let noe man put aſunder: And they tooke one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in the Aſſemblies of the Righteous when all things were cleere Therefore let all theſe things be inquired into, and brought into the Generall meeting And from thence ſome ordred to goe to them and to returne what they Say at your next meeting, And all theſe, before they or any of them are left as heathen, or written againſt, let them be three or four times gone to that they may have Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50854:15"/> order; Soe that if it be poſſible they may come to that which did convince them to condemne their vnrighteous doings that ſoe yee may not leave a hoofe in <hi>Aegypt</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7ly And alſo ſuch as weares their hatts when Friends prayes and are gotten into the old rotten principle of the Ranters, who ſetts up the wearing thereof in oppoſition to the power of God, and therein holds it which is condemned by it, and the power of God is gone over it and them, who are ranted from the truth, And have ſtopped many who were coming into it, that the very world can ſay you are in confuſion and divided, and gone from your firſt principle, who ſaid you were of one heart and one mind and one ſoule and Therefore that ſpirit muſt be cutt off by the Sword of the Spirit of the Lord that they may come to that which at firſt did convince them; And notice muſt be given to the Generall meeting of all theſe things, And from thence ſome muſt be ordered to goe to exhort them that be in ſuch things, to come to the Firſt principle that did at. Firſt convince them, that they may come over ſuch things And Friends muſt ſtand up in the noble ſeed of God to judge the world and all the fallen Angells.</p>
            <p n="8">8ly And in all your meetings let notice be given to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall meeting of all the poore and when yee have hard that there is many more poore belongs to one meeting then to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and that meeting thereby burthened and oppreſſed let the reſt of the meetings aſiſt and help them, ſoe that yee may eaſe one another and help to beare one anothers burthens and ſoe fullfill the Law of Chriſt, and ſoe ſee that nothing be lacking according to the Apoſtles words <hi>(Mark)</hi> nothing lacking then all is well; For the <hi>Jewes</hi> outward though they were as the Starres of heaven and as the Sand of the Sea yet there were not to be a beggar amongſt them according to the Law of God. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Chriſtians in the Firſt age there was a mens meeting Sett up at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to ſee that nothing was lacking which was the Goſpell order according to the Law of Jeſus; And this continued as long they lived in the life, and power and ſpirit of God: But when the Apoſtacy came in and the true Church fled into the wilderneſſe who was to continue there 1260 Dayes, and the witneſſes propheſied in ſackcloth 1260 Days: And the Beaſt was worſhpped juſt ſoe long 1260 Days, and then all things went out of order, and every thing was wanting in the time they worſhipped the Dragon, and the Beaſt, And the Devill made the world like a wilderneſs. But now the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great whore is come and of the Beaſt, and with them the falſe prophet and the Dragon who ſhall be caſt alive into the lake of fire, And the true Church come vp out of the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, and the man child (which was caught up into heaven) come downe again to rule all Nations with a rod of Iron, And the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50854:16"/> marriage of the Lambe is come, and the Lambe and the Saints ſhall have the victory, and the everlaſting Goſpell is and ſhal be preached again, as was amongſt the Apoſtles, and the Goſpell order muſt be ſet vp as was amongſt them, and a mens meeting as was at the Firſt converſion to ſee that nothing be lacking in the Church then all is well, Soe there is not to be a beggar (now) amongſt the Chriſtians according to the Law of<note n="*" place="margin">Chriſt is added in the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out.</note> Jeſus as there was not to be any amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> according to the Law of God</p>
            <p n="9">9ly And alſo all men that hunts after women from woman to woman: And alſo women whoſe affections runs ſome times after one man and ſoone after to another and ſoe hold one another in affection and ſoe drawes out the affections one of another, and after a while leaves one another, And goes to other and does the ſame thing this doing makes more like <hi>Sodom</hi> then Saints, and is not of Gods moving nor joyning where they are not to be parted, For Marriage is Gods ordinance and Gods command one to another, and in that they feele the power of God</p>
            <p n="10">10ly And that notice be taken of all evil Speakers backbiters ſlanderers and fooliſh talkers, and idle jeſters, for all theſe things corrupts good manners, and is not according to the Saints, and holy ones whoſe words are ſeaſoned with Salt miniſtring Grace to the hearers</p>
            <p n="11">11ly And all ſuch who are tale carriers and railers whoſe work is to ſowe diſſention are to be reproved, and admoniſhed, for ſuch doe not bring people into the vnity of the Spirit, but by ſuch doings looſe their own Conditions</p>
            <p n="12">12ly And all ſuch as goes vp and downe to cheate by borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and getting money of Friends in bye places, and have cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeverall, all ſuch are to be ſtopt and judged, as theres a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man tale in her perſon and fleckled in her face, and alſo one <hi>John Harding</hi> who are for judgment and to be condemned</p>
            <p n="13">13ly And if there happen any difference betweene Friend and Friend of any matters if it cannot be ended before the Generall meeting, Let half a dozen Friends from the Generall meeting be ordered to put a ſpeedy end therevnto, That juſtice may ſpeedily done, that noe difference may reſt nor remaine amongſt any, And let your Generall meetings be once every Quarter of a yeare and to be appointed at ſuch places as may be moſt convenient for the moſt of Friends to meete in; Soe that the houſe may be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of all that is contrary to puritie vertue, light life and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and power of God ſoe that Friends may not be one anothers ſorrow and trouble but one another joy and Crowne in the Lord</p>
            <p n="14">14ly and all Friends ſee that your Children be trained vp in the feare of the Lord in Soberneſſe and holyneſſe, and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50854:16"/> and temperance and meekneſſe and lowlyneſſe and modeſty in their apparrell and carriage, and ſo to exhort your Children and families: And teach your Children when they are young, then will they remember it when they are old, according to <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> ſoe that your Children may be a bleſſing to you and not a curſe</p>
            <p n="15">15ly And that Friends do buy Convenient burying places as <hi>Abraham</hi> did who bought a place to bury his dead, and would not bury amongſt the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> and <hi>Cananites</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> was brought out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> and they were buryed in their Grandfather and great Grandfathers burying place; And ſoe Friends to buy decent burying places for your meetings, and to keep out of the Spirit of the <hi>Sodomites</hi> and <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and <hi>Cananites</hi> which corrupts the earth and let them be Decently and well fenced that you may Condemne the world in all things</p>
            <p n="16">16ly And alſo that Friends buy convenient Bookes for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtring of births marriages and burialls as the holy men of God did of old as you may read through the Scriptures that every one may be reddy to give a Teſtimony and Certificate thereof, if need require or any be called therevnto.</p>
            <p n="17">17ly And alſo that all the Sufferings of Friends of all kind of Sufferings in all the County be gathered vp and put together and ſent to the Generall meeting and ſoe ſent to <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Ellis Hoakes</hi> That noe thing of the memoriall of the blood and cruell Sufferings of your Brethren be loſt which ſhall ſtand a teſtimony againſt the murdering Spirit of this world, and be to the praiſe of the everlaſting power of the Lord in the ages to come who ſupported and vpheld them in ſuch hardſhips and cruelties who is God over all bleſſed for ever Amen</p>
            <p n="18">18ly And let inquiry be made concerning all ſuch as pay Tithes which make void the Teſtimony and Sufferings of all our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who have Suffered many of them to death, by which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Widdowes and Fatherleſſe have beene made, and which is contrary to the Doctrine of Apoſtles, and the Doctrine of the Martyrs, and contrary to the Doctrine of the Righteous in this preſent age, all ſuch are to be inquired into and to be exhorted.</p>
            <p n="19">19ly And let Query be made concerning all Priſoners that are poore that they may be relieved, and ſoe incouraged in their Sufferings, and alſo that care be taken for their wives and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, that they do not ſuffer for want of Supply of outward things, And let enquiry be made how many priſoners there are in all the priſons in all your ſeverall Counties</p>
            <p>Let Diligent enquiry be made into all theſe things at every monthly meeting, and at every Quarterly meeting to take care accordingly</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:50854:17"/>
            <p>Deare Friends be faithfull in the Service of God and mind the Lords buſineſſe and be Diligent and bring the power of the Lord over all thoſe that have gaine ſaid it; And all you that be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full goe to viſit them all that have beene convinced, from houſe to houſe, that if it be poſſible you may not leave a hoofe in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and ſoe every one goe ſeek the loſt ſheep, and bring him home on your backs to the fold, and there wil be more joy of that one ſheepe then of the ninety nine in the fold</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Coppies of this to be ſent all abroad amongſt Friends in their mens meetings</hi> G. F.</signed>

            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>All my Friends every where who are gathered in the name of Jeſus Chriſt keepe your meetings according as you did in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, between the 10th and 11th hour when the Prieſt is in the heart of his worſhip, and ſoe you all to be in your meetings feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the bread of life, when the Prieſt and his company are in his and their diſhes and pleaſures; and you then to break vp your meetings, as you feele the power to order you about the third or fourth houre, when the Prieſt is in the heart of his worſhip and ſoe you may go away when he is in his heart, and ſitt over his diſhes and goe away in his heart, This was the practice of Friends in the the beginning Therefore continue in it, and doe not looſe it; keepe your meetings on the Firſt dayes and your weekly meetings in the name of Jeſus that never changes</p>
               <p>And Friends all take heed of ſleeping in meetings and Sottiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and dullneſſe, for it is an ill ſavory thing to ſee one ſitt nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in meetings and ſoe looſe the ſence of the Lord, and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facedneſſe both, and it grieves the vpright and watchfull that waites vppon the Lord to ſee ſuch things And for the Prieſts peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and others that comes into your meetings and to ſee you that come together to worſhip God, And to meete together to waite vpon him to have fellowſhip in his Spirit, for you to ſitt nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is a ſhame and an vnſeemly thing Therefore be carefull and watchfull, and let it be amended, and mind the light and power of Chriſt Jeſus in you and that will condemne all ſuch things, and lead you out of and above ſuch things, and make you watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full one over another for your good</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Let this be read in all your meetings</hi> G. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mem.</hi> This is Spelt and Pointed according to the Copy.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:50854:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
